Edmond Charles Genet Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edmond Charles Genet Papers 1734-1895 (bulk 1789-1793)
MSS22079
Genet, Edmond Charles, 1763-1834
35,000 items
53 containers plus 1 oversize
21.2 linear feet
41 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
French diplomat and first minister of the French Republic to the United States. Correspondence written and received during Genet's diplomatic service in Russia and the United States; also legation accounts, extracts from English newspapers, notes relating to England and America, scientific papers, a memoir prepared by his son, Geo. Clinton Genet, and other descendants, and printed material.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Clark, George Rogers, 1752-1818--Correspondence.; Clinton family.; Clinton, DeWitt, 1769-1828--Correspondence.; Clinton, George, 1739-1812--Correspondence.; Dana, Francis, 1743-1811--Correspondence.; Genet family.; Genet, Edme Jacques, -1781--Correspondence.; Genet, Edmond Charles, 1763-1834.; Genet, Geo. Clinton (George Clinton); Izard, Ralph, 1742-1804--Correspondence.; Michaux, André, 1746-1802--Correspondence.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831--Correspondence.; Montbarey, Alexandre Marie Léonor de Saint Mauris, prince de, 1732-1796--Correspondence.; Noailles, Jean-Louis-Paul-François, duc de, 1739-1824--Correspondence.; Osgood family.; Sartine, Antoine de, comte d'Alby, 1729-1801--Correspondence.; Vergennes, Charles Gravier, comte de, 1719-1787--Correspondence.
Subjects
Diplomatic and consular service, French--England.; Diplomatic and consular service, French--Russia.; Diplomatic and consular service, French--United States.; Political science.; Science.
Places
England--Foreign relations--France.; France--Foreign relations--England.; France--Foreign relations--Russia.; France--Foreign relations--United States.; Russia--Foreign relations--France.; United States--Foreign relations--France.
Occupations
Authors.; Diplomats.
Provenance
The papers of Edmond Charles Genet, French diplomat and first minister of the French Republic to the United States, were obtained by the Library of Congress through gift and purchase, 1918-1955.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Newspapers have been transferred to the Serial & Government Publications Division. Broadsides have been transferred to the Rare Book and Special Collections Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of these papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edmond Charles Genet are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of these papers is available on forty-one reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1763, Jan. 8 Born in France
1777 Secretary to his father in the Bureau of Interpretations, Ministry of Foreign Affairs
1780 Student, Gressen and Berlin, Germany
1780 1781 Served in secretariat of Baron de Breteuil, Vienna, Austria
1781 1783 Assumed offices held by his father
1783 Acting secretary, French legation in England
1787 Sent to French embassy, St. Petersburg, Russia
1789 Chargé ďaffaires, French embassy, St. Petersburg, Russia
1792 Expelled from Russia Appointed French minister plenipotentiary to the United States
1793 Arrived at Charleston, S. C. Toured eastern United States Recalled from United States
1794 Purchased a farm on Long Island, N.Y. Married Cornelia Tappen Clinton
1800 Moved to a farm in Rensselaer County, N. Y.
1814 Married Martha Brandon Osgood
1834, July 15 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edmond Charles Genet (1763-1834) span the years 1734-1895, with the largest concentration of material between 1789 and 1793.
Edmond Genet's brief career as the French Republic's first minister to the United States, and his earlier diplomatic assignments in London and Saint Petersburg, are documented in the first two series of the collection. Genet's early career and education are described in a series of letters from Genet's father, Edme Jacques Genet, and other members of his family, together with draft replies by Genet, dated between 1776 and 1781. Of special interest are several letters of Ralph Izard addressed to Genet, dated 1778-1779, while the latter was chief of the interpreter's bureau at Versailles. Genet's St. Petersburg mission is represented by material in this collection that is not available in the archives at Leningrad. The correspondence series also includes many letters and drafts from officials of the various French ministries, letters relating to the Clinton and Osgood families, and commissions and diplomas, some of which are signed by the kings of France.
Aside from the series of news abstracts prepared by Genet as part of his official duties, a good portion of the remaining notes, drafts, and essays reflect Genet's interest in political theory and scientific research. There also are newspaper clippings, accounts of legation and secret expenses, memoirs by Genet's son, Charles, and miscellaneous papers.
In addition to the above mentioned letters of Edme Jacques Genet and Ralph Izard, the following are prominent correspondents in the collection: George Rogers Clark, DeWitt Clinton, George Clinton, Francis Dana, André Michaux, James Monroe, Charles Gravier, comte de Vergennes, Antoine Raymond Gabriel de Sartine, Jean-Louis- Paul Francois, duc de Noailles, and Alexandre Marie Léonor de Saint-Mauris, Prince de Montbarey.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in ten series:
General Correspondence I, 1756-1895
General Correspondence II, 1761-1821
Copies of Letters, 1740-1823
Diplomatic Despatches, 1740-1792
Speech, Article, and Book File, 1734-1824
News File, 1764-1787
Newspaper File, 1776
Expense File, 1792-1794
Miscellany, 1792
Oversize, 1792
Container List
Available on microfilm. Shelf no. 14,286
- General Correspondence I, 1756-1895 (Box 1-19, Reel 1-10)
  Letters sent and received, extracts from diplomatic despatches, notes, drafts and other papers of Genet and the Genet family.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 27 Oct. 1756-15 Jan. 1771 (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 8 Feb. 1771-25 July 1778 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - 26 July 1778-13 Jan. 1780 (Box 3, Reel 2)
  - 21 Jan. 1780-12 Sept. 1781 (Box 4, Reel 2)
  - 22 Sept. 1781-19 Aug. 1783 (Box 5, Reel 3)
  - 29 Aug. 1783-31 Dec. 1789, undated (Box 6, Reel 3)
  - 15 Jan. 1790-20 Sept. 1792 (Box 7, Reel 4)
  - 26 Sept. 1792-16 Apr. 1793 (Box 8, Reel 4)
  - 17 Apr.-16 June 1793 (Box 9, Reel 5)
  - 17 June-18 Aug. 1793 (Box 10, Reel 5)
  - 19 Aug.-1 Oct. 1793 (Box 11, Reel 6)
  - 2 Aug.-7 Nov. 1793 (Box 12, Reel 6)
  - 8 Nov.-31 Dec. 1793 (Box 13, Reel 7)
  - 1793, undated-23 Jan. 1794 (Box 14, Reel 7)
  - 24 Jan. 1794-5 Apr. 1795 (Box 15, Reel 8)
  - 14 Apr. 1795-27 Mar. 1799 (Box 16, Reel 8)
  - 30 Mar. 1799-15 Apr. 1816 (Box 17, Reel 9)
  - 28 Oct. 1816-18 Sept. 1895, undated (Box 18, Reel 9)
  - Undated (Box 19, Reel 10)
- General Correspondence II, 1761-1821 (Box 20, Reel 10)
  - 1761-1797, 1821 (Box 20, Reel 10)
- Copies of Letters, 1740-1823 (Box 21, Reel 11)
  Transcripts of letters to and from Edmond Charles Genet, his father, Edme Jacques Genet, and his son, Charles.
  Arranged chronologically. Filed separately are French transcripts of several John Paul Jones letters, 1780-1781.
  - 1740-1823 (Box 21, Reel 11)
- Diplomatic Despatches, 1740-1792 (Box 22-37, Reel 12-15)
  Official instructions and extracts to and from Genet, his father, Edme Genet, and others. Also a small amount of correspondence, copies of diplomatic drafts, maps and notes.
  Arranged by origin of despatch and thereunder chronologically.
  - Saint Petersburg, Russia (Box 22, Reel 12)
    - 1740-1783 (Box 22, Reel 12)
    - 1784-1788 (Box 23, Reel 13)
    - 1789 (Box 24, Reel 13)
    - Jan.-Aug. 1790 (Box 25, Reel 14)
    - Sept.-Dec. 1790 (Box 26, Reel 14)
    - Jan.-June 1791 (Box 27, Reel 15)
    - Jul-Dec. 1791 (Box 28, Reel 16a)
    - 1792 (Box 29, Reel 16)
    - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 30, Reel 17)
    - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 31, Reel 18)
    - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 32, Reel 18)
  - Constantinople, Turkey, 1763-1791 (Box 33, Reel 19)
  - Sweden, 1776-1791 (Box 34, Reel 19)
  - Vienna, Austria, 1789-1792 (Box 34, Reel 19)
  - London, England, and Hague, Netherlands (Box 35, Reel 20)
    - 1761 (Box 35, Reel 20)
    - 1762, 1776, 1790-1791 (Box 36, Reel 21)
  - Berlin, Germany, and Danzig, Poland, 1775-1777 (Box 37, Reel 22)
  - Berlin, Germany and St. Petersburg, Russia, 1789-1790 (Box 37, Reel 22)
  - Berlin, Germany, 1791 (Box 37, Reel 22)
  - Hamburg, Germany, 1789-1790 (Box 37, Reel 22)
  - Santa Domingo, 1789-1792 (Box 37, Reel 22)
- Speech, Article, and Book File, 1734-1824 (Box 38-46, Reel 23-34)
  Numerous articles, essays, and notes prepared by Genet with special emphasis on the natural and political sciences. In addition, a compilation of the history of the Genet family (called memoirs) from Edme to Edmond Charles Genet edited by Edmond Charles from notes and drafts left by his father.
  Arranged by type of writing.
  - Scientific papers (Box 38, Reel 23)
    - 1769-1778 (Box 39, Reel 24)
    - Undated (Box 39, Reel 24)
    - Undated (Box 40, Reel 25)
  - Studies relating to England and the English Constitution, 1766-1770, undated (Box 41, Reel 26)
  - Essays on American politics, 1783-1787, undated (Box 42, Reel 26-27)
  - Notes relating to America, 1782-1783, 1786, undated (Box 43, Reel 28)
  - Speeches, 1824, undated (Box 44, Reel 28)
  - Memoirs (Box 44, Reel 29-30)
    - Books I-IX, XII-XIX (Box 44, Reel 29-30)
    - Drafts, 1734-1798 (with gaps) (Box 45, Reel 31-32)
    - Fragments (Box 46, Reel 33)
- News File, 1764-1787 (Box 47-49, Reel 35-37)
  Extracts from English newspapers as well as précis of events in Great Britain and America abstracted from newspapers and personal observations.
  Chronologically arranged.
  - London, England, news abstracts (Box 47, Reel 35)
    - 1783-1785 (Box 47, Reel 35)
    - 1787 (Box 48, Reel 36)
  - American news abstracts, 1783-1787 (Box 48, Reel 36)
  - Extracts from British newspapers, 1764-1775 (Box 49, Reel 37)
  - Miscellaneous extracts, 1765, undated (Box 49, Reel 37)
- Newspaper File, 1776 (Box 50, Reel 38)
  Newspaper clippings from contemporary newspapers relating to America and its war for independence.
  - Clippings from various newspapers, 1776 (Box 50, Reel 38)
- Expense File, 1792-1794 (Box 51, Reel 38)
  Receipts, declared accounts, and personal and official expense vouchers of Genet and others while he was minister plenipotentiary to the United States. Also a small quantity of expense accounts incurred by secret agents of Genet working in the southeastern United States.
  - Legation accounts, secret expenses, 1792-1794 (Box 51, Reel 38)
- Miscellany, 1792 (Box 52-53, Reel 39-40)
  Mainly newspaper clippings, fragments of letters, undated notes, drafts, extracts, and reports.
  - Miscellany (Box 52, Reel 39)
  - Miscellany (Box 53, Reel 40)
  - Passport, 1792 See Oversize (Box 53)
- Oversize, 1792 (Box OV 1)
  Passport.
  Arranged and described according the series and container from which it was removed.
  - Miscellany (Box OV 1)
    - Passport, 1792 (Container 53) (Box OV 1)